Finding Aid for Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies (University of Michigan) Records, 1892-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies (University of Michigan) records
1892-2014
Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.
Graduate School of the University of Michigan. Records include dean's topical files, 1892-1996; files of associate deans; minutes of the executive board; project and grant files detailing faculty and student research; lists of degrees granted; records of fellowships and awards granted by the graduate school and university; and files relating to academic departments and programs, including reviews of degree programs.
87198 Bimu C161 2
242 linear feet
4 microfilms positive and negative
2.44 GB online
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (donor No. 972 ) has been received in various accessions beginning in 1939. The latest accession was added in 2010.
The Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files including search, review, promotion, and tenure files which are restricted for thirty years from date of creation and student educational records which are restricted for seventy-five years from the date of creation.
In addition, records of the Graduate School added to the record group after January 1, 2001 are restricted for twenty years from date of accession in accordance with the university's policy on the records of Executive Officers, Deans, Directors and their support offices. Records in this category are identified with an "ER restricted" note.
The Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 140, 145-151, 192, and online content
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 140, 145-151, 192, 244
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 155-191, 193-243
While the University of Michigan made its first provisions for graduate study in 1845, throughout most of the nineteenth century there were few graduate students to educate. Control of graduate programs was vested in the various university departments. University President James B. Angell advocated, in the late nineteenth century, the establishment of a graduate school, and in the academic year 1891/92 his goal was partially achieved when the College of Literature, Science and the Arts established a separate Graduate Department.
The Graduate Department was unable to coordinate graduate programs outside of the college. To make such coordination possible, the Regents established a university Graduate Department during the academic year 1911/12. This department was independent of any special faculty and was granted its own budget. Its primary purposes were to coordinate graduate education and to promote research. In 1915, through a general university revision of titles, the department became the Graduate School.
As part of its responsibility for promoting research, the Graduate School was made responsible for all university publications in 1913. As early as 1920 the school's governing board advocated the establishment of a separate university press. This was done in 1930, and responsibility for university publications was gradually transferred to the Administrative Committee of the University Press. The final transfer of authority occurred in 1935.
More important than its role of university printer was the responsibility of the Graduate School to dispense university research funds. Most general fund expenses for research, notably the Faculty Research Fund, flowed through the Graduate School, as did many private gifts received by the university to further research. In order to better coordinate the expenditure of this money, President Alexander G. Ruthven suggested in 1929 the establishment of university-wide divisional committees. These interdisciplinary advisory bodies came to have great importance in deciding which requests for support would be funded.
In 1935 the Graduate School's prestige and resources were substantially increased by the bequest of Horace H. Rackham. A total of 6.5 million dollars was received. Four million dollars was put aside as a perpetual endowment, the Horace H. and Mary A. Rackham fund, while the remainder was used to construct a suitable building to house the Graduate School, now renamed the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies. The Rackham Building was dedicated June 17, 1938.
In addition to dispensing research funds, the Graduate School coordinated the efforts of major research projects that were not governed by any other university unit. Examples are the Institute of Public and Social Administration (IPSA), founded in 1936 (now the Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy), and the Bureau of Government, administered by the IPSA. Another example is the Institute for Human Adjustment (IHA), which at its founding in 1937 administered four major programs, the Fresh Air Camp, the Speech Clinic, the Social Science Research Project, and the Bureau of Psychological Services. In 1951 the Division of Gerontology was created under the IHA. A final example is the Statistical Research Laboratory (SRL), founded in 1946. In 1959 the Computing Center was created as a separate division of the SRL. The burden of administration created by overseeing so many large projects proved troublesome. In the 1960s the Graduate School attempted to find suitable university units to become responsible for the oversight of many of these large projects.
Another reason for the transfer of projects was that during the 1950s the Graduate School became a central coordinating body for all university research, taxing the school's resources. In academic year 1947/48 the Committee on Budget Administration of the university directed that all university trust funds supporting research be reported to the Graduate School. In 1959 a vice-president for research was established within the university, the position to be held by the dean of the Graduate School. The decision to combine the posts of vice-president and dean in one person was reversed in the academic year 1964/65. (The positions were temporarily merged for several years in the mid 1980s under Dean Alfred Sussman and then separated again when John D'Arms assumed the deanship of Rackham.)
From the post World War II period until the 1970s the federal government continually increased the amount of funding available from it for research. Most of this money, however, was channeled to scientific and technical areas. To compensate for this imbalance, the Graduate School funneled most university research funds into the humanities and the social sciences. University research money given to scientific and technical areas tended to be seed money, funds to help a faculty member perform basic research necessary to attract a larger, non-university grant.
In 1990, the positions of Dean of Rackham and Vice Provost for Academic Affairs were combined to reflect the close relationship between the Office of the Provost and the Graduate School (later the title of the dean's supplemental administrative appointment was modified to Vice Provost for Academic Affairs -- Graduate Studies). In this dual role, the Dean of Rackham was involved in a number of initiatives in the 1980s and 1990s at the university, including the development of the Institute for the Humanities in 1987 and the reorganization of international programs at the university and establishment of the International Institute in 1993. Within Rackham in the late-1990s, there was a strong emphasis on interdisciplinary initiatives, including the development of the Rackham Summer Interdisciplinary Institute and the Rackham Interdisciplinary Seminars, both in 1997.
Deans of the School of Graduate Studies
1911-1915 Karl E. Guthe
1915-1927 Alfred H. Lloyd
1927-1934 Carl G. Huber
1935-1945 Clarence S. Yoakum
1945-1946 Peter Okkelberg (acting)
1946-1964 Ralph A. Sawyer
1964-1971 Stephen H. Spurr
1971-1974 Donald E. Stokes
1974-1985 Alfred S. Sussman
1985-1995 John D' Arms
1995-1996 Robert A. Weisbuch (acting)
1996-1997 Nancy Cantor
1997-1998 Earl Lewis (acting)
1998-2005 Earl Lewis
2005 Janet Weioss
The records of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies are physically boxed in the order in which the various accessions were received, with the result that continuing record series may be located in several box ranges.
Summary Contents List
Dean's Topical Files 1892-1958 (boxes 1-7) 1958-1985 (boxes 7-14, 60) 1967-1985 (boxes 61-62) 1964-1971 (boxes 74-78) 1947-1986 (bulk 1975-1985) (boxes 79-84) 1970-1971 (Stephen Spurr files) (box 109) 1968-1991 (bulk 1975-1991) (boxes 112-122) 1985-1996 (box 154) 1972-1996 (bulk 1985-1996) (boxes 174-181) 1910-2005 (bulk 1997-2003) (Earl Lewis files) (boxes 196-205) 1971-2010 (bulk 2000-2010) (Janet Weiss files) (boxes 210-214)
Associate Dean for Academic Programs and Student Affairs Meetings File, 1975-1980 (boxes 14-15) Topical File, 1966-1978 (boxes 15-17)
Michigan Scholars in College Teaching Program 1961-1967 Topical Files (boxes 17-18) Correspondence with cooperating colleges (box 18) Departmental correspondence (boxes 18-19)
Research Records Summary and Administrative (boxes 19-23) Project Files (boxes 23-72
University Units 1952-1985 (boxes 85-94) 1970-1991 (boxes 122-133) 1989-1996 (box 187) 1998-2004 (boxes 230-232) 1977-2009 (boxes 195-196, 230-232)
Program Evaluation 1978-1992, Carole Berlin Files (boxes 95-106) 2001-2004 (Digital, Dearborn and Flint) Administrative Files/ 1972-1992 1991-2007 National Research Council Assessment (boxes 215-221) Reviews (boxes 209, 224-227)
Board of Governors Agendas / Correspondence (box 110) Meeting Tapes (box 173) Minutes, 1936-2006, (box 221-224)
Events (boxes 232-236)
Institute for Human Adjustment (IHA) (boxes 110-111)
Projects and Programs (box 111)
Rackham Arthritis Research Unit (box 111)
Administrative Files 1874-1985 (boxes 133-134) Alliances for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (AGEP) (boxes 205-206, 209) Associate Dean for Student Recruitment and Support (boxes 183-187) Assistant Dean for Program Support (boxes 188-189) Board of Governors Minutes (boxes 221-224) Carole Berlin Files (boxes 106-109) Dean's Group Files (box 210) Financial (boxes 206-207) Meetings (boxes 207-208) Miscellaneous Associate and Assistant Deans (box 190) Students of Color of Rackham (SCOR) (boxes 190, 196) Panel on Allocation of Space for Student Organizations and University Involvement with Student Organizations (box 191) Rackham Renovation Records (box 228) Searches (box 195) University Press (box 229)
Faculty research Grants (boxes 135-139)
Degree Lists Degree Lists - Chronological (boxes 141-143 and 145) Degree Lists - Field of Study (boxes 144 and 146-147) Doctoral Degree Lists (box 144 and 147)
Fellowships, Grants and Awards Minority Faculty Development Fund (boxes 148-149) Distinguished University Professorships (box 149) Power Exchange Program (box 150) South African Mid-Career Fellowship (box 150) International Partnership Program (box 151) Raoul Wallenberg Medal and Lecture (box 152) Rackham and University, (box 154) General (boxes 193-194, 207) Graduate Assistance in Areas of National Need Grant Files (boxes 239-240) NIH (boxes 240-241) Catherine Lord Grant Files (box 241) Inactive Grant Files (box 241) NASA Grant Files (boxes 241-242) NSF Grant Files (boxes 241-243) Miscellaneous Grant Files (box 243) Mellon Fellowship (boxes 237-238)
Graduate School Executive Board and Administrative Council Correspondence and Miscellaneous (box 153) Elections (box 153-154) Minutes and Agendas (boxes 155-172)
Dean's Chronological Files (boxes 181-182)
Graduate Student Organizations (boxes 190, 196)
Program Evaluations 1989-2004 (digital files)
Archived Website (online)
Files which are restricted under the personnel and student records policy are located in boxes 140, 145-151, 192, 244.
The records of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies document the administration of the school, its academic programs and research projects and fellowships funded by the school and outside sources. The records include Dean's Files, minutes of the Executive Board and Administrative Council, Academic Unit and Program Evaluation files, and grants administration records.
Records of the Graduate School have been received by the library in numerous accessions, some large others quite small. Some accessions represent continuations or complements to previously received materials. This finding attempts to intellectually integrate continuing or similar record series received in multiple accessions.
The records are organized into a number of series. Among the more significant are:
Deans' Topical File
Research Records
University Units
Program Evaluations
Faculty Research Grants
Degree Lists
Faculty Fellowships, Grants and Awards
Graduate School Executive Board and Administrative Council
In 2008, the Rackham School of Graduate Studies announced that it would become a 'paperless' office and that future accessions to the Bentley Library would be electronic. The materials from 1990 to 2003 were thus digitized by Rackham staff (from the original paper records) and saved as PDF (Portable Document Format) files. As of 2012, these digital accessions comprise two subseries within the Graduate School Executive Board and Administrative Council series and Program Evaluation series.
Subjects:
University of Michigan Near East Research Expedition (1924-1934); Association of American Universities.; Early Modern English Dictionary.; Horace H. Rackham Educational Memorial (Detroit, Mich.); Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; Michigan Council of Graduate Deans.; Michigan Scholars in College Teaching Program.; Middle English dictionary.; Rackham Arthritis Research Unit (University of Michigan); Universities and colleges--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Barbour Scholarships for Oriental Women Committee.; University of Michigan. Biological Station.; University of Michigan. Engineering Research Institute.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; University of Michigan--Graduate work.Graduate work.; University of Michigan--Grants.Grants.; University of Michigan. Institute for Human Adjustment.; University of Michigan. Institute of Public Administration.; University of Michigan. Institute of Social Work.; University of Michigan. Office of Graduate Minority Affairs.; University of Michigan. Press.; University of Michigan--Research.Research.; University of Michigan. Statistical Research Laboratory.; University of Michigan. University College.; University of Michigan. University Council.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; D'Arms, John H., 1934-; Effinger, John Robert, 1869-1933.; Huber, Gotthelf Carl, 1865-1934.; Lewis, Earl.; Lloyd, Alfred H. (Alfred Henry), 1864-1927.; Sawyer, Ralph A. (Ralph Alanson), 1895-1978.; Spurr, Stephen Hopkins.; Stokes, Donald Elkinton, 1927-; Sussman, Alfred S.; Varner, Nellie M.; Weiss, Janet A.; White, Alfred H. (Alfred Holmes), 1873-; Yoakum, Clarence Stone, 1879-1945.
- Dean's Topical Files, 1892-2010
  The Dean's Topical files series is the principal administrative file of the school. It includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of committees, and files relating to academic departments and programs. The series dates from the founding of the school in 1892 through 2010. Dean's Topical have been transferred to the library in multiple accessions and are subdivided into subseries reflecting those accessions. Occasionally an accession represents the files of a single dean, but more frequently a subseries will span the tenure of several deans. There is frequently considerable overlap in the time periods covered by the various subseries. Within each subseries, the files are arranged alphabetically.
  - 1892-1958
    The original accession of Dean's Topical Files is divided into two subseries, 1892-1958, and 1958-1985. The year 1958 represents a general point of division between the two files, but not an absolute one. In particular some pre-1958 material can occasionally be found in the subseries 1958-1985. Among the more significant subjects are the budget, Bureau of Government, Early Modern English Dictionary, Executive Board agendas and minutes, Institute for Public and Social Administration, Rackham Building construction, Statistical Research Laboratory, Dissertation Review Committee, Inteflex, and the Michigan Council of Graduate Deans. Another small accession of 1958-1985 was received later.
    - Admission and Records, 1928-1929 (Box 1)
    - Alice Freeman Palmer Loan Fund, 1921 (Box 1)
    - American Petroleum Institute, 1927-1929 (Box 1)
    - American Scandinavian Foundation, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Appropriations of the Board of Governors, 1936-1955 (Box 1)
    - Army Mathematics Center proposal, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Association of American Universities, 1933-1954; 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Barbour Scholarship Committee, 1925-1929; 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Biological Station Directorship, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - Bishop, William Warner, 1927-1929 (Box 1)
    - Budget of the Graduate School, 1916/1917-, 1955/56; 17 folders (Box 1)
    - Bureau of Government, 1935-1945; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Bureau of Government Budget, 1937/38-1945/46; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Certificates, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Cooperative Stores, 1922 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Definition of the Term Student, 1922/23 (Box 1)
    - Committee on the Naming of University buildings, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Salaries, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Scholarly Publications, 1948-1955; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Computers, 1955-1957; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1945-1960; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Degrees Awarded, Types of, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
    - Doctoral Examination Reports, 1907 (Box 2)
    - Doctoral Thesis Suggestions, 1912-, circa 1915 (Box 2)
    - Early Modern English Dictionary
      (also Middle English Dictionary material)
      - Budget, 1938-1945 (Box 2)
      - Committee Records and Reports, 1939-1946 (Box 2)
      - Fries, Charles G., 1931-1939 (Box 2)
      - Hulbert, James R. and Henning Larsen, editors (Box 2)
      - Knott, T.A., 1938-1941 (Box 2)
      - Kurath, Hans, editor, 1945 (Box 2)
      - Meech, Sanford-accusations and retractions, 1938 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Modern Language Association
        - Basis of Cooperation, 1944-1945; 1964 (Box 2)
        - Editor, 1944-1945 (Box 2)
      - Sisam, Kenneth, Claredon Press, 1931-1943 (Box 2)
    - Effinger, John R., 1927-1929 (Box 2)
    - Engineering Research Council, 1949; 1956-1958; 13 folders (Box 2)
    - Executive Board
      - Agendas and Related Papers
        - 1934-1936, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - 1936-1941, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Minutes, 1892-1951
        - October 1892-August 1915, 1 microfilms located in microfilm cabinet positive and negative (Reel 1)
        - September 1915-August 1937, 1 microfilms located in microfilm cabinet positive and negative (Reel 2)
        - September 1937-August 1943, 1 microfilms located in microfilm cabinet positive and negative (Reel 3)
        - September 1943-June 1948, 1 microfilms located in microfilm cabinet positive and negative (Reel 4)
        - 1945-1951, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Faculty Research Funds Committee, 1928-1935 (Box 3)
    - Fenton Community Project, 1938-1939 (Box 3)
    - Foreign Students, Committee on Admission, 1945-1952; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Frances E. Riggs Fellowships, 1924-1929; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - General Education Board Report, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Gerontology, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Graduate Faculty Meetings, 1943-1958 (Box 3)
    - Graduate Outing Club, 1926-1939 (Box 3)
    - Guggenheim Foundation, 1928 (Box 3)
    - Honorary Degree Material, 1927 (Box 3)
    - Institute for Human Adjustment
      - 1937-1942, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - 1949-1958, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Institute of Public and Social Administration, 1936-1958; 10 folders (Box 4)
    - Joint Committee on the Training of Teachers, 1936-1956; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Management Sciences program, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1921-1930; 1940; 1948; 1956-1958; Undated; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - National Committee on Calendar Simplification, 1929 (Box 4)
    - Near east Research, 1925-1931 (Box 4)
    - North Central Association, 1927-1933; 4 folders (Box 4)
    - President's Committee on Special Needs of the University, 1928-1929 (Box 5)
    - Princeton Lectures, 1920 (Box 5)
    - Quadrangle, 1920 (Box 5)
    - Rackham Building
      - Architect's Correspondence, Smith, Hinchman and Grylls, 4 folders (Box 5)
      - Cornerstone Laying, October 30, 1936 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1933-1952; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Dedication, June 17, 1938 (Box 5)
      - Memorial Plaque (Box 5)
      - Property (Box 5)
      - Seals and Coats of Arms of Other Schools (Box 5)
      - Suggestions, 1938-1939 (Box 5)
    - Rackham Education Memorial, Detroit
      - Correspondence, 1938-1942 (Box 5)
      - Dedication, January 28, 1942 (Box 5)
      - Publications About, 1941 (Box 5)
    - Rackham Fund
      - Arthritis Project, 1937-1950 (Box 5)
      - Flint Project, 1937-1940 (Box 5)
      - Funding Requests, 1942-1959 (Box 5)
      - Governors of Fund, 1936-1941 (Box 5)
      - Influence of Heredity on Senility and Disease, 1940 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Rackham $400,000 Fund, 1939 (Box 6)
    - Rackham Loan Fund, 1933-1936 (Box 6)
    - Rackham Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Rackham Non-university Proposal (Box 6)
    - Rackham Scholarship Fund (Box 6)
    - Rackham Will of Horace H., 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Radiation Policy Committee, 1951-1957 (Box 6)
    - Relation of Education Courses to Requirements for Master's Degrees, 1921 (Box 6)
    - Remission of Fees, 1927 (Box 6)
    - Reports of Departments on Research, 1926
      - A-Z, 7 folders (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Reports of the Graduate School
      - 1919/1920-, 1929/30; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Requirements for Doctorate in Various Departments, 1923 (Box 6)
    - Research Club, 1921-1923 (Box 6)
    - Research Funds and Exemptions from Fees, 1920 (Box 6)
    - Research Reports, 1926-1927 (Box 6)
    - Rhodes Scholarship Applications, 1924; 1926-1927; 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Sabbatical Leaves, 1921-1922 (Box 6)
    - Scholarly Publications, Report On, 1958 (Box 6)
    - Senate Committee on Undergraduate Studies, 1926-1927; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Social Science Research Council, 1932 (Box 6)
    - Social Work, Institute of, 1940; 1943-1950; 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Speech Clinic Reports, 1946-1951 (Box 7)
    - Statistical Research Laboratory, 1946-1954; 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Student Council, 1923-1924 (Box 7)
    - Theses for Master's Degree, 1927 (Box 7)
    - University College, 1927-1928; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - University Council, 1931-1935; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - University of Minnesota Study, 1932-1933 (Box 7)
    - University Museums, 1944-1956; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Use of University Buildings Committee, 1923-1924 (Box 7)
    - White, Alfred H., 1926-1929 (Box 7)
    - Woodrow Wilson Foundation, 1922 (Box 7)
  - 1958-1985
    - A Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Academic Affairs Advisory Council, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Afro-American Study, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Allied Health School Proposal, 1974; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Appeals procedure, 1974-1976; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Appropriations of the Board of Governors, 1958-1961 (Box 8)
    - Association of Graduate Schools, 1964 (Box 8)